Adams family papers
Litchfield Historical Society
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Charles (1845-1864)
    - Rogers, Henry to relatives of Charles Adams Jr., circa 1864 Jun 15 (Folder 21)
      Solicitation card from Attorney Henry Rogers, "pensions, bounty pay procured for discharged soldiers and relatives of deceased officers and soldiers."
  - Adams, Charles Chauncey (1788-1814)
    Charles Chauncey Adams (1788-1814) was the son of Dr. Henry Adams and Sarah Pelton Adams and the nephew of Joseph Adams and Deborah Marsh Adams. He was a printer and newspaper publisher in Poughkeepsie, N.Y.
    - Adams, Charles Chauncey to Adams, Joseph, 1807 Nov 23 (Folder 1)
      Adams expresses sympathy for the death of his uncle Joseph's brother and well wishes for the good health of Joseph's children. Adams regretfully turns down his uncle's offer to come to Litchfield to publish a neutral newspaper, citing the remaining two years on his apprenticeship and perhaps two more after that. Adams indicates he is opposed to newspapers which are affiliated with political parties.
  - Adams, Dinah Wiley (1764?-1811)
    Dinah Wiley Adams (1764?-1811) was married to Rev. Thomas Adams (1764-1797) and was the sister-in-law of Joseph Adams.
    - Adams, Dinah Wiley to Adams, Joseph, 1811 Jun 12 (Folder 1)
      Dinah has traveled to Rehoboth, Mass., "in search of health" and inquires where she might find relatives in New England. She misses her son.
  - Adams, Henry (1794-1842)
    Henry Adams (1794-1842) was the son of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams. He was born in Litchfield. For a time in the 1820s, he was a newspaper publisher in Huntsville, Ala. In 1829, he purchased The Litchfield County Post and renamed it The Litchfield Enquirer. He published the paper until his death by accidental drowning in 1842.
    - Adams, Henry, 1826 (Folder 1)
      Two letters written to his father.
      - Adams, Henry to Adams, Joseph, 1826 Feb 12 (Folder 1)
        Henry writes from Huntsville, Ala., about his health. He also reports Mr. Alden has left Huntsville and Henry is owed $2,000 and will go to court in an attempt to collect it. He expresses his disappointment in his business affairs since arriving in Huntsville six years ago. He inquires about family members and wonders about his future business prospects.
      - Adams, Henry to Adams, Joseph, 1826 May 31 (Folder 1)
        Henry writes from Owego, N.Y., that in the course of his travel from Alabama he has lost or been robbed of about $530. He asks for a loan of $200 and says he will repay it after bringing his business in Huntsville to a final close. Since coming of age, he has never been in so unpleasant a situation as regards money. He also offers news of family and friends.
  - Adams, Henry (1835-1889)
    Henry Adams (1835-1889) was the son of Charles and Julia Hinman Adams.
    - Adams, Henry to Wheelock, Mary Adams, circa 1854 (Folder 1)
      Adams writes to sister about family and friends and his attendance at a church service.
  - Adams, Joseph (1767-1856)
    Joseph Adams (1767-1856) was the son of Rev. Amos and Elizabeth Prentice Adams. For additional information, see his entry in Creators.
    - Adams, Joseph to Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1825 Aug 17 (Folder 1)
      Joseph writes to his wife in Geneva, N.Y., about his travel so far. He was taken very sick in Albany, which continued as he traveled by stage through New York. He is extremely pleased with the country and would leave Litchfield were he a young man. He reports on the health of Mr. Chapman.
    - Barber, Timothy to Adams, Jospeh, 1843 Dec 16 (Folder 2)
      Barber writes from Madison, Ind. with news of his family and its whereabouts.
    - Bates, Buell L. to Adams, Joseph, 1825 Jun 1 (Folder 3)
      Bates writes regarding putting Henry (his son?) out to "some place." His father thinks it best, but he does not agree. He requests that Adams do nothing about "getting a place."
    - Breck, Joseph to Adams, Joseph, 1837 Jan 30 (Folder 4)
      Breck, who is married to Sarah Bullard, a niece of Joseph, writes to inform Adams that his sister Elizabeth has died.
    - Buell, David to Adams, Joseph, 1816 Feb 21 (Folder 5)
      Buell writes from Troy, N.Y., regarding payment of William Baldwin's note, a tombstone to be placed in Troy, and poor business conditions.
    - Bullard, John to Adams, Joseph, 1813 Jan 15 (Folder 6)
      Bullard, who was married to Joseph Adams's sister Elizabeth, writes from Pepperell, Mass. regarding Adams's feeling that Lancaster is a pleasant town, but has high taxes. Still, it would be very agreeable if Adams settled there. Bullard discusses present down business conditions and the ongoing war, the health of his family, activities of his sons Henry and Royal.
    - Bullard, John to Adams, Joseph, 1813 Apr 13 (Folder 7)
      Bullard writes from Pepperell, Mass., that he is glad to hear of the good health of Adams's family, nephew William Adams has died in South Carolina and the estate will need an agent, would Adams be willing to come to Boston, the health of his family, and a legal matter involving Douglas Blanding.
    - Bullard, John to Adams, Joseph, 1817 Aug 9 (Folder 8)
      Bullard writes from Pepperell, Mass., expressing his concerns with Adams's demand for payment. Bullard mentions Amos Lawrence, Giles Richards, and Adams's sister Sally Adams Richards as possible agents for him.
    - Bullard, John to Adams, Joseph, 1818 Jul 21 (Folder 9)
      Bullard writes from Pepperell, Mass., that his son Charles has written to his son Royal to communicate Adams's wishes. Bullard will be happy to visit Adams but not earlier than September. Political affairs in Connecticut have given a shock to many men. Bullard reports on the health of his family and friends.
    - Bullard, Royal to Adams, Joseph, 1809-1813 (Folder 10)
      Royal Bullard (1789-1846) was the nephew of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams.
      - Bullard, Royal to Adams, Joseph, 1809 Mar 8 (Folder 10)
        Bullard writes from Yale about his plans to return to Pepperell, whether his father can attend commencement, and bringing family members to New Haven. He leaves it to Adams to best judge his plan.
      - Bullard, Royal to Adams, Joseph, 1811 May 10 (Folder 10)
        Bullard writes from Boston on his and his Aunt Richards's behalf. Adams son Henry is well. Bullard remembers Joseph well for his money favors while in Connecticut. He reports news about his family and describes his present situations. He hopes to pass the bar and that money he had of Mrs. H. will be called for. It would be extremely difficult for his father to assist him.
      - Bullard, Royal to Adams, Joseph, 1813 Jun 25 (Folder 10)
        Bullard writes from Camden, S.C. regarding Mr. Lang's claim of about $10,000, in which Adams and Mr. Blanding is involved.
    - Chamberlain, Oliver E. to Adams, Joseph, 1843 Feb 10 (Folder 11)
      Chamberlain writes from Amenia Union, N.Y. to inform Adams that he should not be charged for advertising a stage company he no longer owns.
    - Church, Rollin to Adams, Joseph, 1820 Oct 7 (Folder 12)
      Church requests that he enter the name of Mrs. Rollin Church upon Adams's list for domestic manufacturing a pair of worsted stockings for the exhibition.
    - Hartford Fire Insurance Company to Adams, Joseph, 1819 Feb 5 (Folder 13)
      Letter from Walter Mitchell, secretary, appointing Adams surveyor for the company for Litchfield and the neighborhood.
    - Holt, Ebenezer to Adams, Joseph, 1811 Feb 4 (Folder 14)
      Holt, a relative of Adams sister Kezia Adams Holt, requests Adams's assistance in collecting notes. If it can be done in a timely fashion, he will be able to pay a note at a considerable discount.
    - Holt, Philemon to Adams, Joseph, 1811-1812 (Folder 15)
      Holt appears to be a relative of Joseph Adams's sister Kezia Adams Holt.
      - Holt, Philemon to Adams, Joseph, 1811 Mar 7 (Folder 15)
        Holt writes from Willington, Conn., that he has purchased a farm for his son and wishes Adams to assist with collecting notes with which Holt can pay the man from whom he purchased the farm.
      - Holt, Philemon to Adams, Joseph, 1811 Apr 4 (Folder 15)
        Holt writes from Willington, Conn., that he has purchased a farm and wishes Adams to assist with collecting notes. The man from whom he purchased the farm is in want of money.
      - Holt, Philemon to Adams, Joseph, 1812 Aug 10 (Folder 15)
        Holt writes from Willington, Conn., seeking Adams's advice regarding the validity of a deed for land that is subject to an action Capt. Hitchcock is about to commence.
    - Hurlbut, Samuel to Adams, Joseph, 1842 Dec 8 (Folder 16)
      Hurlbut, writing from Baltimore, encloses a draft for Adams's bill.
    - Lawrence, Amos to Adams, Joseph, 1823 Jul 26 (Folder 17)
      Amos Lawrence (1786-1852) married Sarah Richards, the daughter of Sarah Adams Richards and niece of Joseph Adams. He writes from Boston that Adams's sister's condition is very comfortable. He gives news about his family's activities and health.
    - Lawrence, Amos to Adams, Joseph, 1845 Feb 1 (Folder 18)
      Lawrence, writing from Boston, gives a thorough accounting of family members alive and dead. He states his philosophy of philanthropy and discusses feelings towards his wealth and children.
    - Lawrence, Amos to Adams, Joseph, 1851 Apr 27 (Folder 19)
      Lawrence, writing from Boston, declines to give introductions in all cases, but Mr. Bulkley may say that Mrs. Bulkley is a relative of his children. He reports on his and his family's health and that he is afflicted because of the death of a favorite nephew, Robert Appleton.
    - Lovell, Joseph and Elizabeth Partridge Lovell to Adams, Joseph, 1818 May 9 (Folder 20)
      Lovell, who was married to Joseph's aunt Jemima (Adams) Lovell before she died, reports from Medway, Mass., on the health of the family.
    - May, James to Adams, Joseph, 1820 Apr 14 (Folder 21)
      May, husband of Joseph Adams's daughter Betsey, reports from Catherine, N.Y., that conditions are favorable and Amos will do better there than in Litchfield.
    - Peck, Tracy to Adams, Joseph, 1818-1844 (Folder 22)
      Three letters from Tracy Peck, who married Joseph Adams's sister Sally Adams, writing from Bristol, Conn.
      - Peck, Tracy and Peck, Sally Adams to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1818 Oct 2 (Folder 22)
        Peck reports the birth of a daughter.
      - Peck, Tracy to Adams, Joseph, 1822 Dec. 3 (Folder 22)
        Peck reports all are well, except for Joseph, who is quite sick. He discusses the claim of Sarah [Null?].
      - Peck, Tracy to Adams, Joseph, 1844 Mar 5 (Folder 22)
        Peck would like Adams's opinion as to the value of his daughter Sally's share of the property of the late Henry Adams. Mary Adams is anxious to buy out the share of the same.
    - Richards, Giles to Adams, Joseph, 1798 Feb 25 (Folder 23)
      Richards, who is married to Joseph's sister Sally Adams, writes from Boston regarding claims of the Joseph's late brother Thomas Adams. Richards provides an accounting. He also relates family news.
    - Spencer, Truman to Adams, Joseph, 1842 May 1 (Folder 24)
      Spencer writes from Camden, N.Y., regarding his subscription to The Litchfield Enqurier.
    - Starr, William to Adams, Joseph, 1820 Dec 18 (Folder 25)
      Starr, writing from Goshen, Conn., relates that Adams had a complaint lodged against Starr and Guy Wadhams for playing cards the day before Thanksgiving. He would like to resolve the matter and asks what the fine is, wishing that Adams would be as reasonable in their fines as he consistently can.
    - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1814 (Folder 26)
      Two letters written in Washington, D.C., while Tallmadge was serving in the U.S. House of Representatives.
      - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1814 Feb 16 (Folder 26)
        Tallmadge writes that he finds that no further aid is needed from him to obtain Adams's money in South Carolina, but if he needs it, he shall "very cheerfully afford it." If the weather permits, he shall be glad if Adams would survey several of his properties.
      - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1814 Mar 5 (Folder 26)
        Tallmadge has written to Mr. Huntington on the subject. If he needs any further aid from Adams "to make a statement for the assessor, please to afford it." Tallmadge reports on appropriations made in the House.
    - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1816 (Folder 27)
      - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1816 Feb 7 (Folder 27)
        Tallmadge discusses a transaction he will conduct on behalf of Adams relative to the value of "D'ft on Charleston" and the sale of Adams's "D'ft" to a gentleman in Georgetown. He relates percentages and specifies which banks are to be used to make payment.
      - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1816 Mar 11 (Folder 27)
        Tallmadge reports on the sale of Adams's "D'ft." He has received payment and purchased a bill on New York at 10 percent premium.
    - Tallmadge, Benjamin to Adams, Joseph, 1823 May 3 (Folder 28)
      Tallmadge, writing from Litchfield to Adams in Brooklyn, relates details of Tallmadge's trip to Litchfield via New Haven. He delivered Adams's letter to his wife. Adams's family is all well and since Mrs. Adams will write soon, he will not go into further reporting "domestic matters." He reports on several recent deaths which have occurred in Litchfield.
    - Wolcott, Oliver (1823-1856), circa 1845 Mar 31 (Folder 29)
      Wolcott sends an invitation to Adams on behalf of the Whigs of Litchfield to attend the polls and then enjoy "suitable refreshments" at the Mansion House.
  - Adams, Joseph (1838-1870)
    Joseph Adams (1838-1870) was the son of Charles and Julia Hinman Adams.
    - Adams, Joseph to Adams, Charles, 1862 May 8 (Folder 1)
      Adams writes from Terryville, Conn., to thank his mother for $3 with which to buy Charlie a hat. He describes how Charlie will not keep a hat on. He recalls the recent sad deaths of Sarah and Frankie in Terryville and reports on the health of the family. He is away on business half the time. He reports on his garden. Willie is off to school and supposes Ella will comfort him if he is homesick.
  - Adams, Julia Hinman (1810-1869)
    Julia Hinman Adams was the second wife of Charles Adams. They married in 1830. He was previously married to Jane Hinman Adams (Julia's sister), who died in 1827.
    - Adams, Julia Hinman, 1851-1852 (Folder 1)
      Two letters, one to her father and one to her daughter.
      - Adams, Julia Hinman to Hinman, Scovil, 1851 (Folder 1)
        Adams writes from Litchfield to her father about sickness in and news of her family, that she is tired and dispirited, and about news of friends.
      - Adams, Julia Hinman to Wheelock, Mary Adams, 1853 Aug 22 (Folder 1)
        Adams writes to her daughter saying that it would be nice if she and Julia were back home. She reports on family news and visits by relatives.
    - Adams, Julia Hinman, 1862-1867 (Folder 2)
      Four letters to family members.
      - Adams, Julia Hinman to Adams, Mary, 1862 May 22 (Folder 2)
        Adams writes from Buffalo to her daughter about family and friends she sees, her tour of Buffalo, and her husband's and her sadness over the recent death of daughter Sarah.
      - Adams, Julia Hinman to unnamed son, 1862 May 28 (Folder 2)
        Adams writes from Buffalo about her impressions of the city, encountering several Sisters of Charity, and news of family and friends.
      - Adams, Julia Hinman to Adams, Charles, 1864 Nov 17 (Folder 2)
        Adams writes from Terryville, Conn., to her husband about the health of Joseph, the weather and thinking of him, her health, and family news. Also on the sheet is a letter from her daughter Ella Adams to Ella's sister Mary.
      - Adams, Julia Hinman to Adams, Charles, 1867 Jun 18 (Folder 2)
        Adams writes from Brooklyn, N.Y., to her husband about visiting with Joseph in Plymouth, meeting up with Mr. McKee en route to Brooklyn, stops along the way, family news, the children are well, and what she is eating.
      - [?] to Adams, Julia Hinman, circa 1860s (Folder 2)
        Empty envelope.
    - Curtiss, Hannah E. to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1860 Jan 26 (Folder 3)
      Curtiss writes from Hartford about the health of friends, the weather, her sore hand, and indelible pencils and obtaining a highly recommended ink. She received "that letter" from her mother, who thinks she should go to Ravenna as soon as the canal opens and keep house. She thinks she should rather stay in this part of the world.
    - How, James (1840-1869) to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1864 Mar 13 (Folder 4)
      How writes to his mother-in-law from Brooklyn that it has been ten months since they were married and they are more happy each day. He writes about his activities, including his work for charitable institution, City Dispensary, and news from family, including from Charlie in camp.
  - Adams, Sarah MacMurphy (1806-1901)
    Sarah MacMurphy Adams married John Marsh Adams, son of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams.
    - Adams, Sarah McMurphy to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1842 Jun 17-18 (Folder 1)
      Adams writes from Augusta, Ga., about her health and that of her family, gladness that Charles is going to settle in Litchfield, and the transfer of her and her husband's interest in the real estate of Henry Adams to his sister Mary. On the same sheet is notarized and signed statement by John Marsh Adams and Sarah Adams transferring their interest as referenced in the letter.
  - Adams, Sarah (1840-1862)
    Sarah Adams (1840-1862) was the daughter of Charles and Julia (Hinman) Adams.
    - Adams, Sarah, 1855-1859 (Folder 1)
      Three letters to her parents.
      - Adams, Sarah to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1855 Dec 10 (Folder 1)
        Adams writes from Hart Seminary in Plymouth about school life, activities, what she is reading, and news of some of the other girls.
      - Adams, Sarah to Adams, Charles, 1859 Jun 7 (Folder 1)
        Adams writes from Bath, N.Y., that she arrived three hours late because an engine conveying a freight train exploded outside of Port Jervis. She offers her account of the explosion and its aftermath. A man who introduced himself as Mr. Sanford said her father intended to return to Litchfield. She reports family news.
      - Adams, Sarah to Adams, Julia Hinman, 1859 Oct 22 (Folder 1)
        Adams writes from Terryville, Conn., that sister Emma asked to her to write and ask her mother to send a slop pail and foot tub for a bath tub for baby. Adams did not sleep well and is beginning to lose her faith in the blisters. She has made a visit long enough.
    - Letters from friends to Adams, Sarah, 1856-1859 (Folder 2)
      - Rogers, D. to Adams, Sarah, 1859 Nov 8 (Folder 2)
        Rogers writes from New Haven about a letter written but not sent, the value of reading, her headache and a walk, an upcoming visit by Clara and how she loves her friends, and wonders about the conditions of Adams's eyes.
      - Rogers, D. to Adams, Sarah, circa 1859 Nov (Folder 2)
        Letter fragment in which Rogers writes about Clara leaving and the house feeling different, her homesickness for Litchfield, her headache today, and her having wasted the day.
      - Stoddard, F. E. to Adams, Sarah, 1856 Jun 1 (Folder 2)
        Stoddard writes from Seymour that he was in New Haven at the same time as Mary but did not see her. Stoddard would like to see Mary and Sarah sometime this summer. Stoddard has started taking music lessons in New Haven. Stoddard's family's black girl has run away and they are without help.
      - [?], Maria to Adams, Sarah, 1856 Feb 17 (Folder 2)
        Maria writes from Plymouth about letters she has received, her schooling, and fellow students.
    - Rogers, Henry W. to Adams, Sarah, 1859 Aug 5 (Folder 3)
      Adams writes from Buffalo to his niece about Sarah's nice words about Julia, family news, reading, and his activities.
  - Baldwin, Ella Adams (1852-?)
    Ella Adams Baldwin was the daughter of Charles and Julia Hinman Adams.
    - Baldwin, Ella Adams to Adams, Charles, 1870 Feb 20 (Folder 1)
      Baldwin writes from Brooklyn about listening to public speakers, letters she's received, attending church, visiting Harriet De Puy, making many visits to New York, turning eighteen tomorrow, returning home, and Joel Hinman.
  - Bulkley, Mary Adams (1830-1900)
    Mary Adams Bulkley was the daughter of John Marsh and Sarah MacMurphy Adams.
    - Bulkey, Mary Adams, 1839, 1868 (Folder 1)
      - Bulkley, Mary Adams to Adams, Joseph and Adams, Deborah Marsh, 1839 May 31 (Folder 1)
        Bulkley writes to her grandparents about news of her sisters, the new baby's name, sending presents, and the scarlet fever that is in and about town.
      - Bulkley, Mary Adams to Adams, Charles, 1868 Jun 30 (Folder 1)
        Bulkley writes to her uncle about visiting next week with her family, provided he finds this an agreeable arrangement.
  - Bullard, Henry Adams (1788-1851)
    Henry Adams Bullard (1788-1851) was the son of Rev. John and Elizabeth Adams Bullard. He was the nephew of Joseph Adams.
    - Bullard, Henry Adams, 1832-1833 (Folder 1)
      Two letters written from Washington, D.C. to his uncle Joseph Adams while serving in the U.S. House of Representatives from Louisiana.
      - Bullard, Henry Adams to Adams, Joseph, 1832 Apr 17 (Folder 1)
        Bullard writes that he is grateful for his uncle's letter with interesting details of himself and his family. Since leaving New England, Bullard has had no opportunity to become acquainted with that branch of the family. He relates details about his family. The Jackson heresy has not tainted him and he hopes to see the day when the present misrule will be overturned. He hopes to be able to visit Litchfield in the fall.
      - Bullard, Henry Adams to Adams, Joseph, 1833 Feb 28 (Folder 1)
        Bullard writes that he visited with Charles, who travelled with his wife and son to Baltimore. Bullard is eager to return home after a long absence. Unfortunately, he was unable to visit Adams because one of his children was sick and later died. There was constant alarm about cholera. He has heard from Aunt Richards, who is feeble. He discusses the new tariff.
  - Coggswell, Elizabeth Rowland (1802-?)
    Elizabeth Rowland Coggswell (1802-?) was the niece of Joseph and Deborah Marsh Adams.
    - Coggswell, Elizabeth Rowland, 1828, 1830 (Folder 1)
      Two letters written in Cincinnati to Elizabeth's uncle Joseph Adams.
      - Coggswell, Elizabeth Rowland to Adams, Joseph, 1828 Nov 25 (Folder 1)
        Coggswell writes that she hopes to hear more often from Litchfield and misses her family and friends. They are living comfortably and rent from Mr. Woodward. She lost her son. There has been a great revival of religion. She tells of visits and hearing from family members.
      - Coggswell, Osmond and Coggswell, Elizabeth Rowland to Adams, Joseph, 1830 Nov 8 (Folder 1)
        Osmond and Elizabeth Coggswell write that they sorry to have taken so long to write after visiting Litchfield. They describe the travel back to Cincinnati. They spent time with Mr. Collier and his family. Mr. Richards is building a large manufactory in Dayton and all in good health.
  - Dana, Rev. Malcolm McG.
    - Dana, Rev. Malcolm McG. to Hubbard, John H., 1864 Jun 9 (Folder 1)
      Two letters regarding the condition and transportation of Charles Adams (1839-1864), badly wounded in the Civil War Battle of Cold Harbor.
  - Deming, Frances Adams (1847-1901)
    Frances Adams Deming (1847-1901) was the daughter of Charles and Julia Hinman Adams.
    - Deming, Frances Adams to Adams, Sarah, circa 1860 Jun (Folder 1)